<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mri on The Mouse Imaging Centre Blog</title>
    <link>/blog/tags/mri/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mri on The Mouse Imaging Centre Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/blog/tags/mri/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Highlights From APPNING and ISMRM 2018</title>
      <link>/blog/post/2018-08-10_ismrm-highlights/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/post/2018-08-10_ismrm-highlights/</guid>
      <description>Jacob’s Highlights I recently attended the Workshop on Animal Population Imaging (APPNING 2018) held after the ISMRM conference in Paris. It was a well run workshop highlighting the benefits and troubles with large scale animal population imaging (https://appning2018.sciencesconf.org/).
Several Highlights from the workshop:
Quantitative Connectomic Histology Presented by GA Johnson from Duke University
 Used Diffusion Tensor Imaging to assess how the brain was connected in the mouse. Attempt to determine the structural connectivity of mouse brain and compare with the tracer studies performed at the Allen Brain Institute  Tractograms currently have more invalid than valid bundles, and therefore they are attempting to be as accurate as possible Goal was to push the technology as hard as possible to get the best resolution and images possible  First scan that pushed the boundaries was a 120 direction DTI scan with b-values up to 4000 s/mm2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Relative Volumes Matter</title>
      <link>/blog/post/2018-03-05_why-volumes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/post/2018-03-05_why-volumes/</guid>
      <description>Intro Figuring out how one group’s brain is different from another’s is a big part of neuroscience. MRI-neuroanatomy – the study of the sizes of brain regions – is a wonderful tool for this job and makes up a sizeable chunk of what we study. MRI operates in a lovely middle ground in the scales of neuroscience. It is strongly related to macroscale features of the organism, including sex, behaviour, etc; but can also inform us about the effects of microscale factors – such as gene expression.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding and playing with peaks in RMINC</title>
      <link>/blog/post/2018-02-08_peaks-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/post/2018-02-08_peaks-intro/</guid>
      <description>So, peaks. When producing a statistical map, it’s good to get a report of the peaks (i.e. most significant findings). RMINC has had this support for a while now, though it has remained somewhat hidden. Here’s a bit of an intro, then.
I will walk through the example we used from the Mouse Imaging Summer School in 2017, which is data from this paper:
de Guzman AE, Gazdzinski LM, Alsop RJ, Stewart JM, Jaffray DA, Wong CS, Nieman BJ.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>